Finding Aid for Medical School Diversity and Career Development Office (University of Michigan) records, 1980-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Medical School Diversity and Career Development Office (University of Michigan) records 1980-2004 1991-2003
University of Michigan. Medical School Diversity and Career Development Office.
0730 Bimu 2
The Diversity and Career Development Office helps to develop and implement programs to support the University of Michigan's Medical School's recruitment, retention, and career development of outstanding individuals from underrepresented and diverse backgrounds. This collection contains materials detailing the DCDO's committee work, program design and implementation, and various reports defining and detailing diversity issues surrounding the University-wide Medical System.
3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Records were transferred to the Bentley Historical Library in December 2006. (Donor No. 9827 ).
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
Medical School Diversity and Career Development Office records are closed under the Executive Records policy.
The record group includes restricted material in the following categories:
Executive Officer Records -- Boxes 1-3
The University of Michigan Medical School (UMMS) established the Diversity and Career Development Office (DCDO) under the direction of Associate Dean, Dr. David Gordon in the fall of 2002.
The Diversity and Career Development Office has its origins with the Medical School's Diversity and Career Development Committee (DCDC) created in 1996. To address diversity issues the DCDC was formed to obtain faculty, staff and trainee input on diversity issues and to recommend programmatic solutions. The DCDC was composed of faculty leaders from each of the departments within the Medical School, and was divided into five task forces: Faculty Affairs, Medical Student and House Officer Affairs, Graduate Student and Postdoctoral Fellow Affairs, Medical School Staff Affairs, and Community Relations.
The DCDO is now known as the Office for Health Equity & Inclusion, established in 2013. Similar to the purpose of the DCDO, the office leads efforts, advises, and coordinates initiatives to enhance inclusion, increase diversity, and promote equity within the Health System. One of OHEI's overarching goals is to recruit, educate, train, employ and retain highly qualified, diverse individuals to become leaders in educational, clinical and research programs. OHEI has started a Diversity Network to spread information about various initiatives and events related to diversity and started the Program for Multicultural Health, which conducts culturally appropriate health promotion, education, and research programs for surrounding communities. They also sponsor Investing in Ability, a series of events promoting awareness of various disabilities.
The Diversity and Career Development Office (DCDO) records consist of 3 linear feet and span the years from 1980 to 2004. The records contain materials detailing the DCDO's committee work, program design and implementation, and various reports defining and detailing diversity issues surrounding the University-wide Medical System. The records are organized into five series: Topical, Programs, Committees, Reports, and Related Historical Documents. Within each of these series, documents are organized alphabetically by folder title and chronologically within each.
Subjects:
Affirmative action programs in education--Michigan.; Health services accessibility--Michigan.; Medical personnel--Recruiting--Michigan.; Medical students--Michigan.; Minorities--Medical care--Michigan.; Minorities in medicine--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Medical School.; University of Michigan. Medical School Diversity and Career Development Office.
- Topical 1992-2002
  The first series, Topical, includes materials relating to affirmative action, funding requests, diversity statements and proposals for development.
  - Affirmative Action 1996, 1999 (Box 1)
    [ER RESTRICTED until July 1, 2027 ]
  - Affirmative Action Press Briefing (Washington DC) March 2003 (Box 1)
  - Diversity and Career Development Efforts for the Medical School Proposals 2000-2001 (Box 1)
  - Funding Requests 1998-2001 (Box 1)
  - Medical School Enrollment Projections 1993, 1995-1999 (Box 1)
  - Meeting with M3 and M4 Minority Students 1999 (Box 1)
  - Mission and Programs 2006 (Box 1)
  - Recruitment 1992-1996, 1999-2000 (Box 1)
  - University of Michigan Medical School (UMMS)
    - Association of Multicultural Scientists (AMS) 1995 (Box 1)
    - Diversity Audit 1995-1996 (Box 1)
    - Diversity Statement undated (Box 1)
    - Minority Faculty 2000 (Box 1)
  - W. K. Kellogg Foundation 2001-2002 (Box 1)
- Programs, (1993-2004
  The Programs series includes the majority of the material. Projects like Health Occupations Partners in Education (HOPE), Health Professional Partnership Initiative (HPPI), and the Ventures in Education Project are documented through proposals, teaching materials, applications and reports. The HOPE Project, Ventures in Education and HPPI are interrelated and a researcher should consider investigating all three for comprehensiveness. Of particular interest is the Essentials of Leading a Diverse Workforce training program and its follow-up reports.
  - Essentials for Leading a Diverse Workforce
    - E-Learning Course 2004, 1 optical disks CD-ROMs (Box 1)
      (contains a PC reliant CD-ROM)
    - Training Program 2001-2003 (Box 1)
    - Quarterly Report May 2003 (Box 1)
    - Second Quarterly Report October 2003 (Box 1)
    - Final Report October 2004 (Box 1)
  - Health Occupations Partners in Education (HOPE)
    - Annual Progress Report 1999-2003, 5 folders (Box 1)
    - A Day in the Life of a Medical Student, 2000 (Box 1)
    - Executive Committee-Meeting Minutes and Agendas 1999-2000 (Box 1)
    - Grant Proposal & Supporting Documents 1998, 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Health Sciences Council 2001-2003 (Box 1)
    - Institutional Review Board Application 1998 (Box 1)
    - Kellogg Foundation Annual Report 2001, Videotape, Betacam SP (Box 1)
    - Mentoring/Saturday Program Committee 1999 (Box 2)
    - Newspaper Clippings 1998-2004 (Box 2)
    - Partnership Council
      - Correspondence and Miscellaneous 1999 (Box 2)
      - Meeting Minutes and Materials 1999-2000 (Box 2)
    - Presentations undated (Box 2)
    - Program Administration undated (Box 2)
    - Saturday Program Health Career Exploration Series 1999 (Box 2)
      contains photos
    - Site Visits 1998-2003, 3 folders (Box 2)
    - Statistics 1997-2000 (Box 2)
    - Student Newsletter 1999-2003 (Box 2)
    - Summer Academy 2000 (Box 2)
    - Summer Academy-Final Report 1999-2000, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Summer Science Academy 2002 (Box 2)
    - Ypsilanti Public Schools Advisory Committee 1999 (Box 2)
  - Health Professional Partnership Initiative (HPPI)
    - Correspondence, Notes and Budgets 1998 (Box 2)
    - Grant-Proposal 1997 (Box 2)
    - National Meetings 1998, 2000 (Box 2)
    - Site Visit 2001 (Box 2)
  - Project 3000 by 2000, 1993-2001 (Box 2)
  - Turner African American Services Council (TAASC) Health Guide Project 1998-2000 (Box 2)
  - University of Michigan Medical School Pipeline Program 1999-2001 (Box 2)
  - Ventures in Education/Summer Science Academy
    - Correspondence 1993-1999 (Box 2)
    - Finances 1994-1998, 2003 (Box 2)
    - Meeting Agendas and Notes 1993-1996 (Box 2)
    - Proposal 1993-1994 (Box 2)
    - Public Relations Material 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - Reports 1993-1999 (Box 2)
    - Site Visits 1995-1996 (Box 2)
    - Statistics 1993-1995 (Box 2)
- Committees 1993-2003
  The Committees series contains materials of the Diversity and Career Development Committee (DCDC) and the University of Michigan Medical School's (UMMS) Diversity/Multicultural Committee. Meeting minutes, agendas, notes and correspondence are retained to illustrate the functions and issues discussed by the committee as well as the creation of policy.
  - Diversity and Career Committee (DCDC) (Box 3)
    - Administration 1996-2003, 2 folders (Box 3)
    - Community Relations Task Force 1997-1998 (Box 3)
    - Correspondence 1997-1999 (Box 3)
    - Faculty Task Force 1996-1999 (Box 3)
    - Medical Students/House Officer Task Force 1996-1998 (Box 3)
    - Membership 1998 (Box 3)
    - Notes undated (Box 3)
    - Reports 2000 (Box 3)
    - Task Force on Graduate Students and Postdoctoral Fellows 1996-1997 (Box 3)
  - Diversity Steering Committee-Meeting Minutes 2003-2004, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan Medical School (UMMS) Diversity/Multicultural Committee
    - Correspondence 1993-1995 (Box 3)
    - Meeting Minutes and Agendas 1993-1995 (Box 3)
    - Reports 1993-1994 (Box 3)
- Reports 1989-1998
  The Reports series contains reports from various investigations into the range of diversity within the University of Michigan Medical System. Completing the collection is a series of Related Historical Documents, containing materials about minority recruitment at the Medical School, minority scholarships and reactions to discrimination and harassment created prior to the establishment of the DCDO.
  - Cultural Diversity Assessment 1996 (Box 3)
  - Diversity Program Report, April 1996 (Box 3)
  - Recommendations for an Organizational Mentoring Program, 1995-1996 (Box 3)
  - Update on Student Retention and Academic Progress at the University of Michigan, 1978-1982 1989 (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan Health System Organizational Culture Inventory Report 1994-1998 (Box 3)
  - University of Michigan Medical Center-Total Quality Diversity Effort: A Four-Year Progress Report, 1996 (Box 3)
- Related Historical Documents 1980-1993
  - Minority Recruitment
    - Correspondence & Notes 1980, 1984-1990 (Box 3)
    - Reports 1981-1992 (Box 3)
    - Statistics 1982-1989 (Box 3)
  - Minority Scholarships 1991-1993 (Box 3)
  - Racial/Sexual Discrimination 1988 (Box 3)
  - Task Force on Minority Recruitment and Retention 1986-1989 (Box 3)